<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: C, | Kaitlin Poskaitis]]></title>
  <link href="http://katiepru.github.com/katiepru/blog/categories/c-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://katiepru.github.com/katiepru/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-01T11:53:44-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://katiepru.github.com/katiepru/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kaitlin Poskaitis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prefix Tree Implementation in C]]></title>
    <link href="http://katiepru.github.com/katiepru/blog/2013/03/09/prefix-tree-implementation-in-c/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-09T20:45:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://katiepru.github.com/katiepru/blog/2013/03/09/prefix-tree-implementation-in-c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Basic Concept</h2>

<p>A prefix tree (sometimes called a Trie), is a data structure typically used for
storing and sorting large lists of words in an efficient manner. A prefix tree
is very similar to a standard binary tree, only with each node having 26
children instead of just 2. A prefix tree starts with a root node, which does
not contain data relevant to any word, but rather acts as a starting point. If
we are using the standard English alphabet, this root node will have pointers to
26 children, one for each letter of the alphabet. Each of these nodes will also
have 26 children, and so on.</p>

<h2>Node Contents w/ Code</h2>

<p>Most implementations of prefix trees share a basic Node structure used for
storing the data:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Character</strong>: each node, with the exception of the root node, represents a
letter in the alphabet. The root node can be any character that is not in the
alphabet. I personally use a space as the root character, as it is most often
used as a word delimeter.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Boolean is_word</strong>: A boolean is needed to tell whether or not a full word
was formed and ended at the current node. Because it is a tree, each node has a
unique path to it from the root node. Simply traversing through the tree and
checking whether these booleans are true is an easy way to obtain all of the
words that were stored in the tree. Also, the value of the boolean does not
affect whether or not the node can have children.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Pointer Array</strong>: We also need a data structure to hold all of the pointers
to the node's children. Since we are typically working with a finite, relatively
small alphabet, an array will work just fine. Each index in the array can
represent a letter (i.e. a = 0, b = 1, etc), and the array at each index will
hold a pointer to a child node.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Pointer to Parent</strong>: A pointer to the parent node is useful for backtracking
up the tree in order to determine the current word given a node.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Below is the C code for defining the struct (called a TrieNode):</p>

<p>```c</p>

<p>typedef enum {false, true} bool;</p>

<p>typedef struct TrieNode
{</p>

<pre><code>char c;
struct TrieNode *parent;
struct TrieNode **children;
bool is_word;
</code></pre>

<p>} TrieNode;
```</p>

<h2>Properly Creating and Destroying TrieNodes</h2>

<p>Before we can begin building the prefix tree, first we must be able to correctly
create and destroy TrieNodes without any memory leaks. First, we will deal with
creating TrieNodes. Below is a function to do so:</p>

<p>```c
struct TrieNode <em>create_trienode(char c, struct TrieNode </em>parent)
{</p>

<pre><code>struct TrieNode *node = malloc(sizeof(struct TrieNode));
node-&gt;c = c;
node-&gt;parent = parent;
node-&gt;children = malloc(26*sizeof(struct TrieNode));
node-&gt;is_word=false;
return node;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This function returns a pointer to a TrieNode struct and takes in a character
and a pointer to the parent node as arguments. It then allocates memory for the
new struct, which we assign to the variable <code>node</code>. It then sets the values of
<code>char c</code> and <code>struct TrieNode *parent</code> according the the arguments. It then
allocates memory for the children array, assuming there are 26 letters in the
alphabet. The size of this array can be changed to suit any alphabet. Lastly, we
assume that the node is not a word when it is created, so we set <code>is_word</code> to
false, although this can be changed later in the program if need. We return the
pointer to the node that we allocated memory formed stored in the variable
<code>node</code>.</p>

<p>Now that we can properly create a node, it is also important that we can destroy
it as well without and memory leaks. Below is a function to do that:</p>

<p>```c
void destroy_trienode(struct TrieNode *node)
{</p>

<pre><code>int i;

if(node==NULL) 
{
    return;
}

for(i=0; i&lt;26; i++)
{
    destroy_trienode(node-&gt;children[i]);
}

free(node-&gt;children);
free(node);
return;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>There are a few important things happening in this function. First, we can see
that the function is of type void and takes in a pointer to a TrieNode struct as
an argument. This is because C is a pass-by-value language, so passing in the
actual struct would not affect the struct outside of this function. The first
thing we need to do in this function is check if the pointer is NULL, as we
cannot destroy NULL. If it is null, we simply return as there is nothing else to
do. Next, wen need to recursively destroy all of the node's children before we
can destroy the node as there will be no way to access them once the current
node is gone.  Lastly, we free the children array and then the node itself.</p>

<h2>Building the Prefix Tree</h2>

<p>Now that we are able to create and destroy TrieNode structs, we can begin to
actually build the tree. The function we will use will read in a file and build
a prefix tree from the contents of that file. This function will assume that
words consist of at least one letter, that words are case-insensitive, and that
words are delimited by any non-letter character. These assumptions can be
changed if needed.</p>

<p>First, we will assume that the function return a pointer to the root node of
the tree and takes in a valid, non-NULL file pointer as an argument. Therefore,
the function definition would look like this:</p>

<p><code>c
struct TrieNode *create_tree(FILE *file)
</code></p>

<p>Next, let's initialize all of our variables to stay pedantic-compiant.</p>

<p><code>c
struct TrieNode *root = create_trienode(' ', NULL);
struct TrieNode *ptr = root;
int character;
int converted;
int buffer;
</code></p>

<p>The variable <code>root</code> will be what we return at the end of the function, as it is
the new root of the prefix tree. Next, <code>ptr</code> will be used to traverse the
tree as needed. <code>character</code> will be the current character we are at
in the file. <code>converted</code> will be used to convert <code>character</code> into
an int between 0 and 26. Lastly, <code>buffer</code> will be the
next character in the file, and is only needed in cases where the file does not
end in a newline character to delimit the last word, as shown below:</p>

<p><code>c
character = fgetc(file);
buffer = fgetc(file);
</code></p>

<p>Now, we can begin a loop through the file. The first thing to do is to convert
<code>character</code> to its lower-case form, as this is case-insensitive.</p>

<p>```c
while(character != EOF)
{</p>

<pre><code>character = tolower(character);
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Next, if the character is a letter, we need to create a node for it and insert
into the tree (if it doesn;t already exist). We do this by populating
<code>converted</code> with the number of the current letter in the alphabet (starting with
0). We then check if the current node we are on already has a child node in the
<code>converted</code> position of the array. If not, we create one. We then advance <code>ptr</code>
to <code>ptr-&gt;children[converted]</code>, as shown below:</p>

<p>```c
if(isalpha(character))
{</p>

<pre><code>converted = character - 97;
if(ptr-&gt;children[converted] == NULL)
{
    ptr-&gt;children[converted] = create_trienode(character, ptr);
}
ptr = ptr-&gt;children[converted];
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Next, we need to check if the current word is complete. This can happen if
<code>character</code> is not a letter or if <code>buffer</code> is EOF. If this is the case, and we
are not on the root node, then we need to mark the current node as a word and
set <code>ptr</code> to the root so we can start again, as shown below:</p>

<p>```c
if(ptr != root &amp;&amp; (!isalpha(character) || buffer -- EOF))
{</p>

<pre><code>pte-&gt;is_word = true;
ptr = root;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Lastly, we need to advance <code>character</code> and <code>buffer</code>:</p>

<p><code>c
character = buffer;
buffer = fgetc(file);
</code></p>

<p>Putting it all together, we have a finalized function to create a prefix tree
from a file:</p>

<p>```c
struct TrieNode <em>create_tree(FILE </em>file)
{</p>

<pre><code>struct TrieNode *root = create_trienode(' ', NULL);
struct TrieNode *ptr = root;
int character;
int converted;
int buffer;

/*This handles if file does not end with a newline*/
character = fgetc(file);
buffer = fgetc(file);

while(character != EOF)
{
    character = tolower(character);

    if(isalpha(character))
    {
        converted = character - 97;
        if(ptr-&gt;children[converted] == NULL)
        {
            ptr-&gt;children[converted] = create_trienode(character, ptr);
        }
        ptr = ptr-&gt;children[converted];
    }
    if(ptr != root &amp;&amp; (!isalpha(character) || buffer == EOF))
    {
        ptr-&gt;is_word = true;
        ptr = root;
    }

    character = buffer;
    buffer = fgetc(file);
}

return root;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This covers how to build a prefix tree from a file. Next, we will cover
applications for this data structure.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
